<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food &amp; Drink</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 15:21:07 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 15:21:07 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Superhero Muffins</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I love cookbooks. Yes, I know that you can find a recipe for almost anything online, and as such, a big, hardcover cookbook might feel a little archaic. Even if I'm likely to turn to the Internet to find a recipe, there's something about reading my way through a printed collection of recipes that I enjoy immensely. I always look forward to the end-of-year recommendations of &amp;quot;the best,&amp;quot; and I often buy a couple. This year, I already had purchased a copy of Roxana Jullapat's &lt;em&gt;Mother Grains&lt;/em&gt;, which I saw on several lists. And I ordered Jesse Szewczyk's &lt;em&gt;Cookies: The New Classics&lt;/em&gt; even though I hardly need more cookie recipes to try. But it was &lt;em&gt;Rise and Run&lt;/em&gt; by Shalane Flanagan and Elyse Kopecky that has really won me over. And frankly, the book encapsulates everything I've been trying to do with my &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/muffins.html&quot;&gt;muffin experiments&lt;/a&gt;: making something healthy to eat pre- and post-workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've never been a runner — or an athlete of any sort, so their previous bestseller, &lt;em&gt;Run Fast Eat Slow&lt;/em&gt;, wouldn't have caught my attention. But now I am. Both. I've started running, training for my very first 5K in March. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it's no surprise I'd never heard of the authors superhero muffins. Hashtag superhero muffins, even. (I did discover that I'd bookmarked the original superhero muffin recipe — I'd just never baked it.) But having read the cookbook cover-to-cover — remember, they're not just a collection of recipes; they're arguments about how/what/why to eat! — I've decided to rethink my workout meals, incorporating the superhero muffins into my diet in lieu of the protein bar that I'd typically wolf down before heading to the gym or onto the yoga mat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I've advanced in my training — from complete novice to beginner — I've learned a lot about what I need to be eating before and after I workout. While I've been focused on hitting my protein goals, many of the protein bars I've eaten have been geared towards folks who are on a keto diet. I'm actually recognizing that I need more carbs (and a bit of caffeine) to do my best, and as such the high fat, high protein snacks aren't really cutting it. I also want something pretty digestible as there's nothing worse than bending over to do a deadlift or squat and having my guts protest loudly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the superhero muffin. I'm not going to include the recipes here because I just baked directly from the cookbook — the everything bagel superhero muffin, that is — and it seems like you can either buy the book or get a recipe &lt;a href=&quot;https://runfasteatslow.com/blogs/news&quot;&gt;from the authors' website&lt;/a&gt;. That said, I'm going to work my way through all the superhero mufin recipes. As the name suggests, the one I've tried so far, the everything bagel superhero muffin, is a savory muffin, and it's incredibly filling (coming in at about 270 calories per pop). It's perfect with a little cream cheese, but just fine on its own too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-12-29-muffin2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I love about the &lt;em&gt;Rise and Run&lt;/em&gt; cookbook in general and the superhero muffin recipes in particular is that the text indicates if the muffin is good for recovery, for endurance, for digestion, and so on. I don't seem to have any issues eating then working out — I do try to give myself at least 30 minutes so that I don't cramp up and drown or whatever. It's actually the whey powder in protein bars that seems to cause me much more intestinal grief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started reading the cookbook and felt as though the authors had done everything I really wanted to do with my muffin experiment. The project felt a little superfluous. But I'm going to continue with it nonetheless — keep trying to make different kinds of muffins that I'll eat &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt;-workout, starting off my mornings with the superhero and then progressing from there. I'm sort of hoping too that by following these particular muffin recipes closely — recipes that are already designed with athletes in mind — that I can greatly improve what I'm baking and eating for myself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 07:16:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/superhero-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/superhero-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Protein Powders in Muffins</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 9&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#recipe&quot;&gt;Jump to the Recipe&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons that I started this muffin experiment was to try to get away from the protein bar fare that relies so heavily on protein powders — whey, egg white, pea, collagen or otherwise. Every morning, I do drink a smoothie that includes whey protein powder. But I've found that if I drink that &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; eat a protein bar, my stomach isn't at all pleased. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a challenge some days to hit my protein consumption goals, particularly on days when I'm not eating meat — something I plan to do more of in the new year. As such, I wanted to experiment with higher protein content ingredients in my muffins — higher protein flours or fats, for example — to see if I could replace the ol' protein bar as a pre- or post-workout meal. That said, protein bars contain &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of protein — about 20 grams — and that's hard to achieve with just almond flour and almond butter (or the like). Frankly, it's hard to even come close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I've avoided adding protein powder to any of my recipes as the quick fix for boosting their protein levels. I'm not a fan of some of the popular &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; websites that are really centered on baking with supplements — sponsored content, I imagine. That said, I am weighing starting to add protein to my recipes — although it'll likely be collagen as 1) it's what I have in the pantry, 2) I don't want to overdo it on the whey, and 3) collagen doesn't dramatically change the texture of the baked good. Collagen is not a complete protein, of course. But I'm less concerned about that as I'm not relying on it as my sole source of protein.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Protein Pumpkin Muffins with Pumpkin Seed Butter&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe for gluten-free, paleo pumpkin protein muffins on &lt;a href=&quot;https://paleoglutenfree.com/recipes/gluten-free-paleo-pumpkin-protein-muffins/&quot;&gt;the Gluten Free Paleo website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 45 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 12&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 108&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 c pumpkin puree&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 c pumpkin seed butter (or 2 c pepitas if making butter from scratch)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 c almond flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 medium banana&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs collagen peptides&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs maple syrup&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs coconut flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp nutmeg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp ginger&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;To make the pumpkin seed butter, roast 2 cups of pepitas in a 300 degree oven for 15 minutes, stirring occasionally. Allow them to cool, then grind them in a food processor for about 15 minutes until they become butter. (After the five-minute mark, you'll start to see the shift from crumbs to paste.) Salt to taste.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 and line muffin tins with paper liners.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, whisk together the dry ingredients (flours, baking powder, spices, salt).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the wet ingredients. Whisk until blended. (You can use a food processor for this step. But, as always, be careful about overmixing your muffin batter.)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pour the dry mixture into the dry mixture and stir just until combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Fill muffin tins.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15-20 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for a couple of minutes, then remove from muffin tins and transfer to a wire rack to cool completely.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original recipe calls for almond butter, but I decided to try making pumpkin seed butter for this version. Pumpkin seed butter is quite comparable to almond butter in terms of protein, fat, and carb content. I was a bit worried that the green color of the pepitas — and hence, the green color of the butter — would mar the look of the muffin. But I used a batch of some really beautiful homemade butternut squash puree that was a vibrant orange, and the color of the muffins turned out fine. The pumpkin seed butter — which I forgot to salt, oops — was quite nutty, and I've been enjoying a tablespoon of it in my morning smoothies this week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-12-29-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to make these again, I would probably make 8-9 muffins rather than 12 as they're quite small. I also followed the original recipe's instruction to use a blender to mix the batter, something I won't do again as I think it leads to overmixing. But otherwise, this is a great recipe. Does it give me the 20 grams of protein of a protein bar? No. But does it wreck my innards like an overdoes of whey does? No! (Of course, collagen peptides to give some folks gastrointestinal distress, so your mileage may vary.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two tablespoons of collagen doesn't really add that much protein to a muffin, but I probably will start incorporating it into some of my future recipes.&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/protein-powder-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/29/protein-powder-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tea in a Time of COVID</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I decided to quit drinking coffee. As I traveled a lot, I found it incredibly tiresome to be so beholden to caffeine each morning. I'd have to plan the start of my day around locating and consuming the drink, lest I suffer the headaches and lethargy of withdrawal. No doubt, some places I traveled had incredible coffee, and it was so pleasurable to kick off the morning with a small cup of espresso or the like. But some places had terrible coffee — the stuff kept warm for hours in a drip coffee carafe that was never that great when freshly brewed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I switched to drinking tea — caffeinated still, but far less so than the Americanos that I'd previously consumed. I didn't wake up thinking about the caffeine blast that was necessary to launch myself into the day. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But finding a good cup of tea, particularly when one's traveling about the US, is as challenging as finding a good cup of coffee — even more so, arguably, since thanks to the Starbucks-ification of coffee consumption, most folks have a decent idea of what &amp;quot;good&amp;quot; coffee should taste like. And, of course, that green and white maiden is ubiquitous. It's hardly the best coffee, but it's reliably good, as the standardization of chain restaurants demands such things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn't the equivalent of Starbucks for tea drinkers. (And my god, bubble tea does not count here.) At far too many restaurants, you'll still be served with a little carafe of water and a stack of tea bags, as though steeping a Tetley tea bag in warm water will produce anything other than disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I'm not sure that I'm that amazing at making my own tea at home. Reading the classic set of instructions penned by George Orwell — &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.orwellfoundation.com/the-orwell-foundation/orwell/essays-and-other-works/a-nice-cup-of-tea/&quot;&gt;A Nice Cup of Tea&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; — underscores how poorly. I use tea bags a lot of the time (although once I finish this particularly large box of Twining's Earl Grey, I am going back to loose tea). I don't use a tea pot. As such, I don't warm the pot or even my mug before I infuse the leaves. I don't give it a good stir. I use an electric kettle, and I'm not sure that I always wait for the water to be at a really rapid boil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my credit, I don't use sugar. I don't add my milk first — and I use oat milk, which Orwell didn't have to reckon with. I don't reuse my tea bags, something I did for a while until Kin jokingly commented that he earned enough money to use a fresh tea bag each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orwell's essay was written during the post-war rationing, and I wonder if I re-used tea bags because that's how I saw my mother drink her tea: a balled-up tea bag sitting in teaspoon on the counter. Why did she re-use them? Was it a remnant of growing up in post-war Britain? Or was it less about rationing from the war and more about rationing from living in the US, where decent tea bags — in the Seventies, surely — were hard to find. I don't remember her squirreling tea away in her suitcase when we traveled home from a visit to family in the UK. I don't remember her receiving a parcel with tea bags as a gift. So perhaps she had to devise her own rationing system — I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vaguely remember instructions from Granny about how to make (and pour) tea properly. But again, I don't recall if she was a milk first person. She certainly allowed us to sweeten our tea. Indeed, tea with milk and sugar, served in a little mug with bunnies on it, was something I was given when, as a child, I was sick with the flu. I think it was the only time I drank out of those cups. I still have the saucer somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the sort of archeology of cooking practices — my own, my family's, my culture's — that I want to write more about here. As we remain holed up in the apartment, thanks to the pandemic, I guess I'll practice getting better at making tea, savoring team, and thinking about why on earth this sort of thing matters so much to me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/22/tea</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/22/tea</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Muffin Frustration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 8&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#recipe&quot;&gt;Jump to the Recipe&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second batch of muffins in a row that I'm really not thrilled with. The taste is fine, but the consistency is far too &amp;quot;stodgy,&amp;quot; as Paul Hollywood would probably describe them. Part of this stems from my experimentation with various gluten-free flours. This week's recipe, for example, was made with oat flour (and the previous batch, almond and amaranth). These tend to make much denser baked goods, but I believe I can still make them lighter. I need to rethink how I do my troubleshooting and recipe testing, because I'm not giving myself an opportunity to improve before moving on to another combination of ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More broadly, I'm also rethinking my whole breakfast situation as I'm not going to eat store-bought protein bars any longer. I'm consuming way too much fat as most of these are &amp;quot;keto-friendly&amp;quot; and I need a bigger shot of carbs for my weightlifting mornings. I've ordered a cookbook called &lt;em&gt;Rise and Runs&lt;/em&gt;, that involves morning food and rituals — including god help me, running. I'm hoping it'll help me find something else to start my day. I do still love my muffin, Siggis, and granola combination, so the muffin project will continue. And I'm still interested in high protein, good fat, low sugar baking. I just want to make some decent goddamn muffins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this recipe only gets me partly there.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Miso Honey Oat Flour Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe for honey oat flour muffins on &lt;a href=&quot;https://hungryhobby.net/honey-oat-flour-muffins/&quot;&gt;Hungry Hobby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 15&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 123&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 c oat flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup kefir&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 c honey&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 eggs&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 and line muffin tins with paper liners.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, whisk together the dry ingredients (flours, baking powder, salt).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the wet ingredients. Whisk until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pour the dry mixture into the dry mixture and stir just until combined. Let sit for five minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Fill muffin papers about three-quarters full.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15-16 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for a couple of minutes, then remove from muffin tins and transfer to a wire rack to cool completely.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with a couple of my cookie experiments, I've added miso to the original recipe. In addition to dialing in the texture of the muffins, I also want to really hone that salted caramel flavor that I think miso can, ideally, provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-12-15-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the problems with this recipe are twofold. First, I used kefir, which was too heavy and made the batter too thick. (The original recipe called for almond milk. Honestly, water might've been better.) And second, oat flour should be given in weights not cups. I mean, this goes for almost all baking recipes, and it's something I need to think about as (if/when) I perfect some of these recipes. Did I use too much oat flour? I don't know. I used three cups worth but was it the right weight?!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/15/muffin-frustration</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/15/muffin-frustration</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Homemade Granola</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I've had some fairly terrible homemade granola in my time. Mostly, it was terrible because it was, in food critic speak, &amp;quot;raisin forward.&amp;quot; I hate raisins. I want my granola to be crunchy, without any surprise mushiness in any of the bites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd never made granola myself until I bought Roxana Jullapart's &lt;em&gt;Mother Grains&lt;/em&gt; cookbook. Her recipe for &amp;quot;Friends and Family&amp;quot; granola is stellar. I've made it several times (and I'll make it again tomorrow). It requires quite an investment in ingredients — particularly nuts and the dried coconut milk powder. But it's totally worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For what it's worth, I've had better success cooking this granola at a lower oven temperature than what the original recipe says.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Friends &amp; Family Granola&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the granola recipe from Roxana Jullapart's Mother Grains cookbook.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 45 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 6&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 468&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;160 g old-fashioned rolled oats&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;40 g raw whole almonds&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;20 g raw walnut halves&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;35 g raw whole cashews&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;40 g pumpkin seeds&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;35 g shelled sunflower seeds&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 Tbps sesame seeds&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 Tbps flaxseed&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;45 g unsweetened shredded coconut&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 Tbps dehydrated coconut milk&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;25 g almond flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp ground cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/8 tsp freshly grated nutmeg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/8 tsp ground cloves&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup honey&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup maple syrup&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup applesauce&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup vegetable oil&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 Tbps vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 300 F. Spray a baking sheet lightly with nonstick spray.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Combine the oats, almonds, walnuts, cashews, pumpkin seeds, sunflower seeds, sesame seeds, flaxseed, coconut, coconut milk, almond flour, and spices in a medium bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a small saucepan, combine the honey, maple syrup, applesauce, oil, vanilla, and salt and heat while stirring constantly, until the mixture is lukewarm. Add the warm liquids to the oat mixture and combine until everything is coated.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spread on the baking sheet and toast for 45 minutes, stirring every 15 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Remove from the oven and spread onto a sheet of parchment paper to cool. Let it cool completely before transferring to an airtight container.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently tried a variation of this recipe — substituting all the varieties of nuts and seeds for just almonds. I also used almond butter in lieu of the oil and almond extract instead of vanilla. It turned out great. (But like I said, I'm making Roxana's original recipe tomorrow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tried one of the recipes in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1021529-banana-granola-with-cinnamon-nutmeg-and-walnuts?action=click&amp;module=Local%20Search%20Recipe%20Card&amp;pgType=search&amp;rank=1&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt; for banana granola. This one tasted great, but it didn't go sufficiently crispy. It was more like eating a banana-flavored oatmeal cookie than eating granola. Kin did not complain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I make this again, I will probably cook it longer at a lower oven temperature to try to get a better crisp.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Banana Granola&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the granola recipe from &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1021529-banana-granola-with-cinnamon-nutmeg-and-walnuts?action=click&amp;module=Local%20Search%20Recipe%20Card&amp;pgType=search&amp;rank=1&quot;&gt;The New York Times Cooking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 15 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 60 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 5&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 325&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup/5 ounces mashed bananas (from about 1 large or 2 small ripe or overripe bananas)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup cup/55 grams dark brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup/50 grams melted virgin coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon ground cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/8 teaspoon ground nutmeg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 teaspoon kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 cups/200 grams old-fashioned rolled oats&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup/30 grams walnut halves, roughly chopped&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 325 F. Line baking sheet with parchment paper.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Combine the oats and nuts in a medium bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Add the mashed banana to a medium saucepan along with the brown sugar and coconut oil. Stir to combine. Cover and cook over medium heat for 2 to 3 minutes, or until the pot comes to a sputtering boil. (You’ll hear it popping.) Cook for another 60 to 90 seconds, swirling the pan often so the mixture doesn’t burn.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Remove the pan from the heat, allow the sputtering to subside, then stir in the lemon juice, vanilla, cinnamon, nutmeg and salt. Fold in the oats and walnuts until combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spread the mixture out on the prepared sheet pan in an even layer. Using a spatula, press the oats down into a layer that is about 1/2-inch thick. Bake for 25 minutes, rotating halfway through, then remove the sheet pan from the oven and, using a butter knife, break the granola into large, 2- to 2 1/2-inch clusters on the baking sheet.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spread the clusters evenly around the pan and bake again until the clusters are a deep golden brown, another 15 to 20 minutes, rotating and tossing halfway through so they don’t burn.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Remove the pan from the oven and allow the granola to cool for at least 30 minutes on the counter to harden slightly. Once the granola has cooled, break it up with your hands into small or medium clusters, depending on preference. Allow to cool completely, at least one more hour.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/08/granola</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/08/granola</guid>
        
        <category>breakfast</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Troubleshooting Muffin Recipes, Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 7&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#recipe&quot;&gt;Jump to the Recipe&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started this project, I wanted to go &amp;quot;all in&amp;quot; on what some people think of as the most annoying part of online recipes: the verbiage before you get to the recipe. That's because, despite there being a recipe at the bottom of each of these posts, the point isn't about the recipe; it's about the lessons I'm learning each time I piece one together. None of these recipes are polished at all. It's an experiment! And this week is no exception — I'm not at all thrilled with how this batch of muffins turned out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to try to make a muffin that was &amp;quot;almond forward,&amp;quot; as someone snooty might say. I used almond flour and almond butter and almond extract. And amaranth flour too, for more nuttiness. They were very, very dense. The flavor was great, don't get me wrong. Ground almonds and eggs are two-thirds of the way to marzipan — one of my most favorite foods. And I suppose I could say that the consistency of these were marzipan-y. Except I help back on the sweetener, so they're missing that final element. They didn't rise very well — like I said, dense. And as the batter was so thick, they didn't have a very nice shape to them either — cooking in almost precisely the same blob as the raw batter filled the muffin tin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to find time to return to some of these recipes that don't quite work out perfectly. And I want to write about troubleshooting recipes. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://delishably.com/baked-goods/How-to-Make-Muffins-Like-a-Pro&quot;&gt;some blog posts online&lt;/a&gt; that purport to help, but they address problems bakers might have made, not problems in the recipe itself. So notes for next time on these almond muffins: more baking powder? Some baking soda? Some oil (not just almond butter)? Some regular flour (not just almond)? A different sweetener? (I used monk fruit, and I have another whole blog post to write on sugar substitutes in muffins).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this week has just been a little crazy, what with the Thanksgiving holiday and a houseguest — my mom, who helped me make brandy snaps for the first time. That's another post I have to write, along with some reflections on holiday baking in general.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Almond Flour, Almond Butter, Amaranth Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe for almond flour muffins on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oliveandmango.com/easy-almond-flour-muffins&quot;&gt;Olive and Mango&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 12&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 153&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 3/4 cup almond flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup amaranth flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup almond butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup kefir&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp almond extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 eggs&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tbs monk sugar, dissolved in 1/3 cup water&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 and line muffin tins with paper liners.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, whisk together the dry ingredients (flours, baking powder, salt).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the wet ingredients. Whisk until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pour the dry mixture into the dry mixture and stir just until combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Fill muffin papers about three-quarters full.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15-18 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for a couple of minutes, then remove from muffin tins and transfer to a wire rack to cool completely.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-12-01-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/01/troubleshooting-muffins-1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/12/01/troubleshooting-muffins-1</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Better Molasses Cookie Recipe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My molasses cookies are Kin's favorite. And I'll admit, they're one of my favorites as well. There's something about that ginger-molasses combination that just hits perfectly. The recipe I use makes a nice soft cookie — one that doesn't dry out on the counter and turn into more of a ginger snap. (Admittedly, these don't last that long.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I've been looking for &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; cookie recipes, I thought I'd take my current recipe head-to-head with a molasses cookie variation. I chose The New York Times Cooking's chocolate-molasses cookie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read the recipe, I knew it would be an unfair comparison. It has fresh grated ginger! Why aren't I adding fresh grated ginger to my usual recipe!? (I think I will from now on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm getting ahead of myself…&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Molasses Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe that appears on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesaltymarshmallow.com/old-fashioned-soft-molasses-cookies/#recipe&quot;&gt;Salty Marshmallow&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 15 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 31&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 127&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup butter, softened&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup molasses&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 1/2 cups flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp ginger&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup granulated sugar (for decoration)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 325 degrees.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, combine the sugar, butter, egg, molasses, and vanilla.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the flour, soda, salt, and spices. Add the wet ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Roll into tablespoon-size balls, then roll in sugar. Place on a baking sheet -- about a dozen fit on a sheet.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 13-15 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool on a wire rack.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Chocolate Molasses Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on Alison Roman's recipe in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1019806-chocolate-molasses-cookies&quot;&gt;The New York Times Cooking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 40 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 33&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 75&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup unsalted butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tbs freshly grated ginger&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 cups flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup cocoa powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp ginger&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup granulated sugar (plus extra for decoration)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup molasses&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 degrees.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Line two baking sheets with parchment paper.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a small pot over medium heat, melt the butter. Add the fresh ginger. Remove from heat and let cool while you prepare everything else.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the flour, spices, soda, and salt.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, combine the sugar, molasses, egg, and ginger/butter. Slowly mix into the dry ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;The dough will be very soft, so refrigerate for about 15 minutes to firm. Then roll into small balls, about the size of a quarter. Roll in sugar, and place on cookie sheet -- about a dozen per sheet.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 6-8 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool on on a wire rack.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-11-24-molasses.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;plain&amp;quot; molasses cookie is, as I said, pretty close to perfect — it's soft, with that granulated sugar texture. The chocolate version bakes at a higher temperature for a shorter amount of time. That's not the only reason they're &amp;quot;fudgier,&amp;quot; of course. But it doesn't have that same molasses cookie texture at all. The chocolate, however, gives it such a rich, dark taste. Despite the addition of the fresh ginger, the ginger flavor didn't overpower the chocolate. And wow damn, I love these. Kin did too, although he's requested I stick with my original recipe for future bakes.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/11/24/better-molasses-cookie</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/11/24/better-molasses-cookie</guid>
        
        <category>cookie</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Muffin Fats</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 6&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;#recipe&quot;&gt;Jump to the Recipe&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my goals with this muffin experiment was to do just that: experiment with different ingredients in order to optimize the health benefits in my daily post-workout snack. As I've written before, I'm not actively avoiding fats, but I am keenly interested in consuming &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; fats and getting the most bang-for-the-buck out of the fats I eat. That means that recipes that call for vegetable oil are easy targets for revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before you revise any recipe, I'd argue, you have to understand why they contain oil in the first place — this is key to all substitutions. If you just say &amp;quot;to hell with it, I'm leaving out the butter altogether in this pound cake,&amp;quot; you're going to be sorely disappointed with the &amp;quot;cake&amp;quot; you bake. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does fat do in a muffin? It slows down the gluten formation caused by the chemical reactions from baking soda and powder — I really need to write about these two ingredients in a future post. As such, oil makes the baked good fluffy and moist. When switching out the oil for a different ingredient, you have to think about both the properties of the oil &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the substitute so that texture and flavor aren't adversely impacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's just say that when recipes say &amp;quot;vegetable oil,&amp;quot; they mean &amp;quot;canola,&amp;quot; even though oil can be made from a ton of grains and fruits and vegetables. Indeed, one of the easiest ways to improve the healthiness of one's cooking is to use better oils: say, olive oil or avocado or coconut. These are high in antioxidants and monounsaturated fat — the &amp;quot;good&amp;quot; kind of fat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could also use nut butters in lieu of oil. The recipe below does just that, using peanut butter in lieu of the avocado in the original (and already very healthy) recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dairy products can also work instead of oil: butter (I mean, sure, why not — there are fewer calories in a tablespoon of butter than in a tablespoon of canola oil, after all), sour cream, yogurt, kefir, buttermilk. These can all work. Is mayonnaise a dairy product? Not sure, to be honest. But as mayo is part oil already, it can be used quite successfully. (I don't think you'll get much of a health boost for this switch, but sometimes you're out of oil and want to make brownies. I get it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common, &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; oil substitute is probably applesauce. But really, almost any fruit or vegetable will work the same way — substitute pureed fruit for the same amount of oil. Bananas. Apples. Pears. Pumpkin. Sweet potato. Beets. Zucchini. Depending on the fruit or vegetable, this will change the taste and appearance of the baked good. And it'll often make the crumb more dense — so you might substitute just half the oil, perhaps, for applesauce. That's still a substantial reduction in fat and calories. It will, on the other hand, increase the carbohydrates in your recipe. (For what it's worth, a cup of pumpkin puree has fewer calories, less sugar, and more protein than applesauce. And you can make a puree out of any winter squash, not just pie pumpkins.)&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Chickpea Banana Peanut Butter Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe for no sugar added chickpea banana muffins on &lt;a href=&quot;https://kellyjonesnutrition.com/no-added-sugar-chickpea-banana-muffins/&quot;&gt;Kelly Jones Nutrition&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 16&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 91&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 cup chickpea flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 ripe bananas&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs applesauce&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup peanut butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tbs vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 tbs oat milk&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tbs apple cider vinegar&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 and line muffin tins with paper liners.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, whisk together the dry ingredients (flour, baking soda and powder, salt, and cinnamon).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, combine the wet ingredients (bananas, applesauce, peanut butter, eggs, vanilla, and vinegar). Whisk until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pour the dry mixture into the dry mixture and stir just until combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Fill muffin papers about three-quarters full.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 15-18 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for a couple of minutes, then remove from muffin tin and transfer to a wire rack to cool completely.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-11-17-chickpea.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bookmarked Kelly Jones Nutrition's recipe for chickpea banana muffins before I started this project, thinking that I'd like to try it for its lack of added sugar and its use of chickpea flour, a flour that is high in protein. And initially, I thought I'd bake the recipe and use it as an excuse to talk about different flours and what they can impart — in terms of nutrition and taste — to baked goods. I'll do that in the future, with another muffin recipe. And I'm trying to amass as much data about different ingredients as I can and find a useful way to present that information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-11-17-chickpea2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I queued up this recipe to bake, I decided that I'd make a few changes to what is already a really great recipe — changes that I undertook as part of the experimental nature of this project. What if I substituted peanut butter for the avocado oil? What if I added some baking powder and salt? Of course, the flaw with my experimental model here is that I'm not actually making the original recipe; I'm just tweaking it to my needs. So I don't know how I'm messing with the flavors or textures. Are these better tasting than the original? I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I really like this muffin a lot. As I was mixing up the batter, I was a little apprehensive because the chickpea flour does smell very strong. And I worried that I'd be eating an unsweetened banana falafel. But I absolutely love how light and fluffy these muffins are. I only had crunchy peanut butter in the pantry, and that's given a bit of texture to them. It's also enhanced the nuttiness of the chickpea flour. But these definitely aren't sweet at all. And as such, I don't think they'd be everyone's cup of tea. Nonetheless, I am really pleased with how they've turned out. (They freeze pretty well too.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll use the chickpea flour and nut butter — separately and in combination — in future recipes, for sure. In fact, the next batch I'm baking includes the latter…&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/11/17/fats-and-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/11/17/fats-and-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Better Oatmeal Cookie Recipe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever I ask Kin what kind of cookies he'd like me to bake, he reminds me of how he ranks his favorites: peanut butter are okay; chocolate chips are good; better are my molasses cookies; and the best are oatmeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a pretty good oatmeal cookie recipe online a while ago. (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#recipe&quot;&gt;Jump to the Recipes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;) It makes a soft cookie — a necessity — but it's just too sweet for me. Kin loves it, and to be honest, when I bake cookies they're really to fit his taste-buds. But &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/2021/10/19/the-better-peanut-butter-cookie&quot;&gt;after trying the miso-peanut butter cookies&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago, I thought I'd see if I could make a batch of oatmeal cookies that were less sweet, with the umami that miso adds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel quite validated about using miso in my baking, incidentally, particularly after Crystelle, a contestant in this season's &lt;em&gt;Great British Bake Off&lt;/em&gt; incorporated it into a couple of her caramel contributions this past week. &amp;quot;It's like salted caramel,&amp;quot; she explained to the skeptical judges. &amp;quot;YES!&amp;quot; I shouted at the television. (She won Baker of the Week too, I might add.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably should have just modified my go-to oatmeal cookie recipe to make it &amp;quot;healthier,&amp;quot; but instead I googled the whole &amp;quot;healthy oatmeal cookie&amp;quot; thing and opted to try one with far less sugar. And as I've never actually baked this recipe before &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; miso, it's hard to judge fully how the addition of that ingredient affected the texture and taste. &lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Soft Oatmeal Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe that appears on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sugarspunrun.com/big-soft-oatmeal-cookies/#recipe&quot;&gt;Sugar Spun Run&lt;/a&gt; blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 40 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 34&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 116&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup unsalted butter, softened&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup granulated sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 eggs&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 3/4 cup all-purpose flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tsp cornstarch&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 tsp cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 cups old-fashioned rolled oats&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Using a stand mixer, cream the butter and sugars.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Add eggs, one at a time, beating until combined. Then add in the vanilla extract.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a separate bowl, whisk together flour, cornstarch, baking soda, salt, and cinnamon.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Gradually add flour mixture to butter mixture until completely combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Stir in oats.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Chill dough in refrigerator for 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 375 and line cookies sheets with parchment paper.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Drop cookie dough by rounded 2 tablespoon-fulls onto the parchment paper -- about a dozen per sheet. (These will spread slightly.)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 10 minutes. They will look underbaked, but will finish cooking on the cookie sheet as they cool.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow cookies to cool completely on cookie sheet.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Not-So-Sweet Miso Oatmeal Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe that appears on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wellplated.com/healthy-oatmeal-cookies/&quot;&gt;Well Plated&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 40 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 24&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 73&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/4 cup quick oats&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup white whole wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup unsweetened applesauce&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons unsalted butter, melted&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs white miso&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;7 tbs honey&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a large bowl, whisk together the oats, flour, baking powder, cinnamon, and salt.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, combine the applesauce, melted butter, miso, egg, vanilla, and honey. Whisk until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pour the wet mixture into the dry mixture and stir just until combined. The dough will be very wet and sticky. Refrigerate for at least 30 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Line two cookie sheets with parchment paper.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Drop 1.5 tablespoon size balls of dough onto cookie sheet - one dozen will fit per sheet. This dough will not spread, so flatten the balls slightly.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 9 to 10 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool on the cookie sheet for 2 minutes before transferring to a wire rack to cool completely.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-11-10-oatmeal.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking and Tasting Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &quot;healthy&quot; cookies were smaller, and as such, it's a bit silly to make too much out of a calorie comparison. &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/2021/10/06/what-is-a-healthy-muffin&quot;&gt;That word &quot;healthy&quot; is a tricky one in any baked good&lt;/a&gt;. I mean, yes, there was less sugar and less fat. &quot;Healthy&quot; though? Hmm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used one tablespoon less honey and one tablespoon less butter than the original recipe, adding in two tablespoons of miso. Other than that, I followed the recipe to a tee. But I wish I'd used old fashioned rolled oats rather than the quick oats that the original suggested. That made them very soft and almost cake-like, and I think the texture that old fashioned oats provides is much better, much... well... oatier. Interestingly, these cookies stayed soft for a long time - is that a result of the fermentation from the miso? I don't know. The peanut butter-miso cookies held their softness as well. (I'm not sure how I'd find the answer here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in-all, I think I'll stick with making the first recipe when baking oatmeal cookies for Kin. But my experimentation with miso - in cookies and otherwise - will continue...&lt;/p&gt;



</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 07:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/11/09/the-better-oatmeal-cookie</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/11/09/the-better-oatmeal-cookie</guid>
        
        <category>cookies</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Leftovers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two servings of paella in the fridge. There's one or two of beef stew. And I'm making chicken pot pie — serves 6, I reckon — for dinner tonight. So tomorrow night: leftovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've done fairly well in reducing the amount of food I cook each evening now that it's just Kin and me for dinner. There are often leftovers, but typically we'll eat them the next day for lunch. But every once in a while, he'll get too caught up in meetings and will miss lunch. (Me, I never miss a meal.) Or I'll make something that the recipe says serves 6 and actually serves 10. That paella, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do have an overabundance of food, I'd like to be able to take a meal out to Ashley, the homeless woman who frequents the park across the street from our apartment building. I even bought some paper plates and plastic forks so that I could do so. Inevitably, she seems to disappear the days that I have something to share. (She did get some birthday cake - I think that's the last time I've been able to feed her.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate throwing out food. Doing so is one of my &amp;quot;triggers&amp;quot; when it comes to food, I suppose, as I was often chastised as a child for not eating everything that was on my plate. I know the stereotypical admonishment is something about &amp;quot;starving children in Africa.&amp;quot; But I remember being told by my aunt that it was more a matter of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; being a wasteful American than any condition of a faraway child. She wasn't wrong, of course. She would invoke wartime Britain — one that I think she was born after, to be honest — in which there was food rationing. And I would (silently) invoke my preference to not eat the fatty bits of a lamb chop. That didn't make me indulgent, for crying out loud. But I always feel like that shirking, embarrassed little girl when I misjudge how much food should be on my plate or in a meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eating leftovers also reminds me of how my mother structured our weekly meals: she'd cook a roast on Sundays, then we'd proceed to have variations on that meat throughout the week. The final night was almost always a curry, which my dad said was because curry powder was used to disguise rotten meat. Racist and wrong. And I've always loved Indian food, even though I tend to not like leftovers. Or rather, I never really liked meat that much, particularly night after night after night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's the problem with leftovers: the repetition of a food I struggled to eat the night before. That's not how I cook or eat today, but the reluctance remains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/11/02/leftovers</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/11/02/leftovers</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
