<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food &amp; Drink</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 11:49:10 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 11:49:10 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Tyranny of CICO (with Chocolate Muffins)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've lost about 40 pounds this year through the only real &amp;quot;scientific&amp;quot; method of weight-loss: CICO — Calories In/Calories Out. That is to say, I've taken in fewer calories than my body has used. Now that I'm weightlifting, however, I'm trying to put on some weight. And it's CICO again, except this time I'm taking in more calories than I burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are probably millions of websites dedicated to weight loss, and I've fallen down quite a few rabbit holes trying to figure out how much to eat and what to eat in order to, at first, lose weight, and now gain muscle. Unfortunately, many of these sites give women — particularly women my age — a ridiculously low number for their TDEE, Total Daily Energy Expenditure, an estimate on how many calories a day one's body burns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an Apple Watch, which does tell me how many energy I supposedly use when working out. But I don't know that the numbers are particularly accurate. Nonetheless, I've started tracking all sorts of data about my health in general, and my diet and exercise specifically. It's pretty easy to see how quickly this sort of attention can turn into disordered behaviors — obsession about food, exercise, weight, and so on. And so it's a real challenge, I think, to find a good balance with one's health, particularly with that notion of CICO hanging over one's head: the relationship between calorie consumption and calorie burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've stopped paying attention to the numbers that Apple gives me for my calorie burn. But I do still monitor my calories — at first I did this with the MyFitnessPal app. But as it is really designed for weight loss, I've recently switched to another app, MacroFactor, that helps me focus on — as the name suggests — my protein macros while smoothing out any daily fluctuations in my weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Watching my calories&amp;quot; hasn't really altered what I cook for dinner each night, although it has made me very aware of portion sizes (and the distortions that occur therein with nutrition labels). But I do plan out what I'm going to eat each day — and how many calories that'll be — in part because I've really struggled with the &amp;quot;bulking&amp;quot; part of my diet. Contrary to the sites that tell me I should eat 1500 calories a day, I need to eat about 2200. That 700 calorie difference? That's about two pounds of body weight — weight I don't want or need to lose, thank you very much. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at 2200 calories — particularly at 2200 calories that are protein-focused — I want my post-workout meals to be really dialed in. I have a rough budget of about 500 calories for pre- and post-workout meals each day: a 230 calorie protein bar, a 120 calorie Greek yogurt, which leaves about 150 calories for a muffin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Yes, we're getting to the part about muffins.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Baking with Chocolate&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chocolate, particularly dark chocolate, boasts a lot of health benefits: antioxidants! lower blood pressure! prevents heart disease! And cacao, the seed pods from which cocoa is made, is also a popular &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; food, with its own set of perks. Plus — and this is really the key — chocolate is delicious. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, there are many good reasons to put chocolate in your muffins. Except adding chocolate — in the form of cocoa powder, cacao nibs, chocolate chips, or what have you — will certainly increase the calorie content of your baked goods. A half a cup of cocoa powder — about the amount that would go into a batch of a dozen muffins — adds about 170 calories to the mix, or about 14 calories per muffin, for example. Adding a third of a cup of chocolate chips adds another 200 calories to the recipe — plus quite a bit of sugar and fat to each muffin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I'd try my hands at making a low-calorie, high-protein chocolate muffin. As there were beets in the weekly CSA, I figured I'd make chocolate beet muffins. Why not. I found a recipe that I tweaked in order to reduce the calories. More details on that below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I &lt;em&gt;over&lt;/em&gt;-substituted; I was not very scientific in my experimentation, and I made too many changes. And as a result, when the muffins came out of the oven quite dry, I'm not sure I can diagnose exactly where I went wrong (or if the original recipe would have been equally flawed). I'll write another blog post soon about how to troubleshoot a failed recipe, but I want my main point to be this: the tyranny of CICO. Don't let &amp;quot;calories in&amp;quot; screw up what you eat. (And don't let &amp;quot;calories out&amp;quot; screw up how much your body needs to move. But that's another story.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's absolutely okay to indulge in something that's full of sugar and fat and calories. And if you force yourself to eat a shitty muffin — for the record, I should clarify, these are not shitty at all and I'm really enjoying them with my morning Greek yogurt — for the sake of your diet, then you're missing out on the beauty of food. Everything you eat should be good — taste good, make you feel good, and ideally good for you. (And chocolate is good for you, the scientists say!) But &amp;quot;good for you&amp;quot; without the other two — taste and pleasure — undermines your whole journey towards health.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Chocolate Cacao Beet Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe that appears on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://minimalistbaker.com/wprm_print/36025&quot;&gt;Minimalist Baker&lt;/a&gt; blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 12&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 130&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 batches of flax eggs (2 tbs ground flax seed plus 5 tbsp water)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup beet puree&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup banana, mashed&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup plain kefir&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbps coconut flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/3 cup whole wheat pastry flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup unsweetened cocoa powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup cacao nibs&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 375 F. Line 12 compartments of standard muffin tin with paper (or grease tin).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Mix together the dry ingredients in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a separate bowl, beat together the flax seed and water, then add the other wet ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Make a well in the center of the dry ingredients and add the wet ingredients. Stir swiftly, until combined. The batter should be thick, but spoonable. Add more liquid if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Gently fold in the cacao nibs.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spoon batter into muffin tins, filling almost to the top.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake 15-20 minutes or until toothpick inserted into center comes out clean.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool for 5 minutes before taking out of the tin.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-27-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original recipe had 1/4 cup of maple syrup and 1/3 cup of brown sugar, along with 1/4 cup of coconut oil. I substituted a banana for the oil. Typically this is a one-to-one swap, but I increased the amount of banana to compensate for ditching the maple syrup entirely. I substituted kefir for unsweetened almond milk in the original. I also decreased the amount of brown sugar in the original, from one-third to just one-fourth a cup. I added some coconut flour, in the hopes of making the crumb soft. Ha. And finally, I used cacao nibs rather than chocolate chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The batter was really dry, and as a result, I think I overmixed it - just to incorporate all the ingredients, I had to stir a lot and add another tablespoon or two of water to moisten it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-27-muffin2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some &amp;quot;Health&amp;quot; Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By ditching the oil and some of the sugar, I did reduce the calories from 175 in the original to just 130. Having never made the original, it's hard to say what I lost in flavor. The original describes these muffins as &quot;fudgy,&quot; and I'm not sure if that's code for &quot;very dense&quot; or if it's code for &quot;pretty chocolatey.&quot; I might try to make these again the next time I get beets in the CSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My changes added just a tiny bit of protein to the muffin from the original; obviously, fat and carbs decreased. And the addition of cacao nibs introduced some caffeine into the mix, something that reminds me to work on a batch of muffins that actually focuses on caffeine - something I like to have before I lift weights (although I usually eat muffins afterwards, so...)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/27/the-tyranny-of-cico-with-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/27/the-tyranny-of-cico-with-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Better Peanut Butter Cookie Recipe</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that it's fall, I'm hoping that I can spend more time baking cookies. This spring and summer, the fruit CSA has kept me busy making cakes and pies and crumbles and the like. And those are all delicious, don't get me wrong. But I love cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm toying with beginning another project here on this site, along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/muffins.html&quot;&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment&lt;/a&gt;. For now, I thought I'd bake two different recipes of the same kind of cookie and see which one Kin and I prefer. That's the funny thing about all the SEO focus of recipe blogging: there are hundreds of blog posts touting &amp;quot;the best&amp;quot; whatever, but I'm not even sure you can really say that the author did a lot of work in identifying their recipe as such. Plus it's all so damn subjective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take peanut butter cookies. I think they tend to be rather dry. I prefer my cookies soft and chewy. Kin agrees. So I found one recipe that touted softness and chewiness, along with another that has a totally different set of ingredients and instructions. These recipes made less than two dozen apiece, so I don't have an overwhelming amount of cookie on hand at the end of this experiment. And I like the idea of actually trying a bunch of cookie recipes before deciding what one is, indeed, the best for our taste-buds here. I mean, I already have a go-to recipe for oatmeal, chocolate chip, and molasses cookies — &lt;em&gt;but what if I'm missing out?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Super Soft Peanut Butter Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lecremedelacrumb.com/best-super-soft-peanut-butter-cookies/&quot;&gt;Creme de la Crumb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 21&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 169&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 cups flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 cup creamy peanut butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup unsalted butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup granulated sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tbs Demerara sugar&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 F. Line two baking sheets with parchment paper.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, whisk together dry ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;With a stand mixer, cream the butter, peanut butter, and granulated and brown sugars until light and fluffy - about 5 minutes. Mix in the egg and the vanilla extract, scraping down the sides, until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Add the dry ingredients to the wet, and mix until just combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Roll dough into 2-3 tbs size balls. Roll in Demerara sugar.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Place balls on cookie sheet, about 2 inches apart. (You should fit 12 on a sheet.) Use a fork to make a criss-cross pattern.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 8 minutes. Do not overbake!&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for 1 minute on sheet, then move to a cooling rack.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Peanut Butter-Miso Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe by Krysten Chambrot that appears in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1020538-peanut-butter-miso-cookies&quot;&gt;The New York Times Cooking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 30 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 21&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 156&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 3/4 cup flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup unsalted butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup granulated sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup white miso&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup creamy peanut butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup Demerara sugar&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a medium bowl, combine flour, baking soda, and baking powder.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a stand mixer, combine the butter, brown sugar, and granulated sugar and beat until light and fluffy - about 5 minutes. Add the peanut butter and miso, then mix in the egg and the vanilla extract, scraping down the sides, until blended.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Add the dry ingredients to the wet, and mix until just combined.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Refrigerate dough for at least two hours, but as long as overnight.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Roll dough into 2-3 tbs size balls. Roll in Demerara sugar.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Place balls on cookie sheet, about 2 inches apart. (You should fit 12 on a sheet.)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 14 minutes. Remove sheets from oven and smack the sheets on the stovetop. This will flatten the cookies. Return to the oven for another 2-4 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Allow to cool for 1 minute on sheet, then move to a cooling rack.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking and Tasting Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &quot;super soft&quot; cookies are fairly soft, but I think it's because they are on the verge of being under-baked. They have retained that stick-to-the-roof-of-the-mouth, cloying sensation of peanut butter. I didn't have any Demerara sugar on hand when I made these and just rolled them in granulated sugar instead (that's what the original recipe suggested), which didn't impart the rougher texture that I'd have prefered. Then again, these are so sweet, I'd say the extra sugar could be optional. I made the batch on Sunday, and while they haven't dried out too much in 48 hours, peanut butter always seems to be a dry cookie. That's something that Kin and I do not want in a &quot;best&quot; version.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the miso-peanut butter combination seems to address that problem. (Although in fairness, I ate one soon after it came out of the oven and cooled. Perhaps it'll be drier and crunchier in a few days. The latter is a big no-no for Kin.) I cut the amount of granulated sugar in half from the original recipe, and I didn't roll these in Demerara sugar either. While I like the saltiness and savoriness that the miso imparts, unfortunately, I think it overpowers the peanut butter almost entirely - and this is after letting them sit overnight in the fridge, which the recipe insisted would &quot;mellow&quot; things out. Depending on how the cookies hold up after a couple of days on the counter, I might try this recipe again with more peanut butter (and probably less butter to compensate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-19-pb.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All-in-all, I think we're still on the hunt for a better peanut butter cookie recipe...&lt;/p&gt;



</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/19/the-better-peanut-butter-cookie</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/19/the-better-peanut-butter-cookie</guid>
        
        <category>cookies</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Substitutions in Muffins (and a Quick Lesson on Buttermillk)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm a big fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com&quot;&gt;The New York Times Cooking&lt;/a&gt;, and I happily pay for a subscription to the website/app. I enjoy browsing the recipes; I even like the recipe recommendations, in part because they seem to operate off of very little personal data about me or analysis of my clicks. Like, I just made pancakes, but thanks for suggesting three more variations. And, if you knew me, you'd know I will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; make rice pudding, NYT. Nonetheless, the &amp;quot;Recommended For You&amp;quot; section consistently gives me ideas for things I didn't even know I wanted to make, and I often use it for inspiration rather than for &amp;quot;search&amp;quot; — that is, for finding a specific recipe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, The Ringer made the case that The NYT Cooking was &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theringer.com/2019/2/7/18214477/nytcooking-comment-section&quot;&gt;the best comment section on the Internet&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; And unlike virtually every other website, I actually do look at the Notes on the recipes I decide to tackle. I think it's a bit of a stretch to say some of these are &amp;quot;the best,&amp;quot; - there's &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/nytimescookingcomments/?hl=en&quot;&gt;an Instagram account that highlights some of the most hilarious ones&lt;/a&gt; - but in all fairness, plenty are useful. (Tonight, for example, I am making &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1014468-coconut-chicken-curry-with-cashews&quot;&gt;chicken coconut curry with cashews&lt;/a&gt;, and I appreciate the note that says the three cups of chicken broth the recipe indicates is far too much.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the comments on The NYT Cooking (and elsewhere) involve substitutions. Angry commenters on The NYT Cooking often complain that a recipe sucks when they've made a silly one: apple cider vinegar for apple cider, for example. (Don't be like that.) Patient food bloggers field these sorts of questions about swapping one ingredient for another in the comment sections of their sites: &amp;quot;what if I substitute rice flour for almond flour?&amp;quot; &amp;quot;can I use oat milk instead of half-and-half?&amp;quot; &amp;quot;I don't have any cardamom. What spice should I use instead?&amp;quot; And so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the recipes I'll be baking as part of this muffin experiment will use substitutions — indeed, that's partly how I'll make these recipes my own. And I'll write lots of posts in the coming weeks and months that will look in detail at how to substitute different flours, different fats, different sugars, &lt;em&gt;and why&lt;/em&gt; into a batch of muffins. But here I want to talk about substitutions in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of good reasons why you'd want to use a different ingredient than one the recipe indicates — most obviously when you don't have that item in your fridge or pantry. Or perhaps the reverse is true: you have a seasonal abundance of an item — say, zucchini — and you'd like to use it up. Or you might want to make a substitution because of health goals, food allergies, or any number of other dietary issues or preferences. Regardless of the reason, &lt;em&gt;the key to changing a recipe is understanding how an ingredient works in the recipe&lt;/em&gt; — how does it affect the taste; how does it affect the chemical reactions that occur while cooking; how does it affect the nutrition; how does it affect the appearance? A recipe isn't a random collection of ingredients; with this in mind, you have to approach substitutions in a somewhat scientific way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How to Substitute Buttermilk&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you type &amp;quot;how to substitute&amp;quot; into Google, you can see by the autocompleted suggestions that one of the most common culinary searches involves how to substitute for buttermilk. A lot of recipes still call for buttermilk, even though I can't imagine it's a terribly popular drink. Buttermilk is like a vestigial organ; it's still in our recipes even though we really don't use it anymore. I mean, not quite vestigial, I suppose - it is great for baking. My grandma cooked a lot with buttermilk; and she always had it in her fridge. (But she drank it straight too — gah!) In the muffin recipe below, that is one of the substitutions I've made from the original. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike my grandma, I do not keep buttermilk on hand, even though I regularly bake from recipes that call for it. I also do not follow what is the Internet's top suggestion for making the substitution: adding one tablespoon of white vinegar to a measuring cup, and then filling it the rest of the way with milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That gives you vinegar milk, which is not remotely the same as buttermilk, even though, yes yes, they're both acidic. Vinegar milk lacks the creaminess of buttermilk, particularly if you're like me and only keep a low-fat milk in stock. (You want the acid - in the buttermilk or in the vinegar - to create the chemical reaction with the baking powder. Baking powder - how does it work - is another future blog post. But long story short, that's why you don't just substitute plain milk for buttermilk.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buttermilk is &lt;em&gt;fermented&lt;/em&gt; milk, and I do, in fact, keep on hand fermented milk in several other forms, namely sour cream, Greek yogurt, and kefir. (I use the latter in my smoothie every morning, so I guess I shouldn't mock my grandma too much for drinking buttermilk.) These are much better options for substitutions, in my opinion, than a thin, vinegar-soured milk.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Buckwheat and Amaranth Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe by Martha Rose Shulman that appears in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1014143-buckwheat-and-amaranth-muffins&quot;&gt;The New York Times Cooking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 16&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 118&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 cup whole-wheat flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3/4 cup buckwheat flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 cup amaranth flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 eggs&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup honey&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 1/2 cup kefir&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup unsweetened applesauce&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup blackberries tossed with 1 tsp all-purpose flour&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 375 F. Line 16 compartments of standard muffin tin with paper (or grease tin).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Mix together the dry ingredients in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a separate bowl, beat together the eggs, honey, kefir, applesauce, and vanilla extract.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Make a well in the center of the dry ingredients and add the wet ingredients. Stir swiftly, until combined. The batter should be thick, but spoonable.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Gently fold in the blackberries.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spoon batter into muffin tins, filling almost to the top.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake 15-18 minutes or until toothpick inserted into center comes out clean.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool for 5 minutes before taking out of the tin.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-13-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original recipe said it made twelve muffins; my recipe makes sixteen. The original said bake for 25 minutes; thankfully I read the comments on The NYT Cooking who told me they'd bake much more quickly than that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I confess: I made a substitution, when I baked these, to my own substitution listsed above: the original calls for canola oil; I've suggested applesauce instead. But when I baked these, I used a homemade pear sauce, because it's pear season. I should have probably skipped the blackberries because it's no longer blackberry season, and the berries I bought were both too large and too tart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-13-muffin2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amaranth gave these a delicate nutty taste, and I plan on making this recipe again (without the berries). I've also got plenty of the flour on hand now to experiment with it in other recipes. Amaranth is a good source of protein and fiber. That said...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some &amp;quot;Health&amp;quot; Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, my experiments with substitutions, while beautifully successful in terms of taste, were a failure when it came to my health goals. I didn't manage to increase the protein substantially by substituting kefir for buttermilk; but I did increase the carbs, including the sugar, by substituting the pear sauce for the canola oil. (The fat content did go down.) These muffins have 4.5 grams of protein, 23 grams of carbohydrates, and 1.4 grams of fat - more carbs and more sugar than the &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/2021/10/04/what-is-a-muffin&quot;&gt;Basic Muffin Recipe&lt;/a&gt;, for crying out loud.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/13/substitutions-in-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/13/substitutions-in-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What to Do with Leftover Muffins?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm only a couple of bakes into this project, and already I am faced with the question: &lt;em&gt;what the hell am I going to do with all these muffins?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, everything goes in the freezer, and I thaw a couple of muffins at a time. A batch of muffins is typically twelve, so if I bake every other week or so, I shouldn't have a problem eating my way through my supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, sometimes, the recipe kind of sucks; sometimes, the batch doesn't freeze well; sometimes, the freezer is full. And sometimes, you want to — maybe you even need to — transform the muffins into something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Might I suggest &lt;s&gt;bread&lt;/s&gt; muffin pudding?&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Muffin Pudding&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on Mark Bittman's Simple Bread Pudding recipe in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1012636-simple-bread-pudding&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 45 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 6 to 8&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 382&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 cups milk&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 Tbsp butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/3 cup sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Pinch of salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;5 to 6 cups of muffins, broken into 2&quot; pieces&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 eggs, beaten&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;fresh fruit (optional)&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 F. Butter a 4 to 6 cup baking dish and fill with the muffin pieces. Add fresh fruit, if desired.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;In a small saucepan over low heat, warm the milk, butter, vanilla, sugar, and salt. Cook until the butter is melted and the sugar is dissolved.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool the mixture. Then add the beaten eggs. Pour this over the muffins.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake for 30 to 45 minutes until the custard is set but still a little bit wobbly.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Serve warm or at room temperature.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-07-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the leftovers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/2021/10/04/what-is-a-muffin&quot;&gt;the batch of Basic Muffins&lt;/a&gt; I made for dessert, along with a couple of fresh plums from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.froghollow.com&quot;&gt;my local fruit CSA&lt;/a&gt;. No surprise, many of the complaints one might have about that recipe - not that sweet, not that rich, not that flavorful - were addressed by the addition of more egg, more butter, more sugar, and more milk. Of course, if one's complaints were those muffins just weren't healthy enough...&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/07/what-to-do-with-leftover-muffins</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/07/what-to-do-with-leftover-muffins</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Is a Healthy Muffin?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always paid some attention to my nutrition. Growing up, my mother made sure that every dinner had a protein, a starch, and a vegetable, for example, as well as the requisite glass of milk for my brother and me. I learned about the food pyramid in school. Cartoon PSAs taught me that &amp;quot;You are what you eat&amp;quot; and that &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/U3jgo5ea_zc&quot;&gt;cheese and crackers were a good choice for snacking&lt;/a&gt;. Much to my family's chagrin, I became a vegetarian when I left home at age 16 — I'd never really liked meat — but didn't really think much about protein until I became pregnant at 20. All that is to say, I've paid &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; attention to my nutrition, but I've actually known very little about it, other than the received knowledge from school, family, and television.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that my attention has turned to my health and well-being, I'm trying to learn more. But wow, I see so much of the conflicting messaging — the &amp;quot;science&amp;quot; and the bullshit — about what we should be eating, about what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; should be eating as someone who's very physically active (and trying to put on muscle through weight-training). And what makes it worse, I'd argue, is that the more you search online for answers or products, the more you get ads that try to sell you on the latest trend: keto, paleo, whatever. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you search for healthy recipes, you also run into similar sorts of problems — both with the business of &amp;quot;clicks&amp;quot; and the business of &amp;quot;health.&amp;quot; Recipe blogging is a finely-tuned SEO machine. The photos — let me tell you — are gorgeous. The prose isn't always &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad. But the recipes, particularly when you're interested in items that are &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; or that have more protein, are pretty hit-or-miss. Indeed, I've found that in order to boost the protein levels, many of these recipes simply include protein powder. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take this one, for example:&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Banana Buckwheat Protein Muffins&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the recipe from &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitseats.com/recipes/banana-buckwheat-protein-muffins&quot;&gt;kits.eats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 12&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 132&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;200 g bananas (about 3 small bananas)&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup Greek yogurt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup maple syrup&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;100 g buckwheat flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;60 g whey isolate protein powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 tsp baking soda&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup cacao nibs&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 350 F. Line 12 compartments of standard muffin tin with paper (or grease tin).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Mash bananas in a medium bowl. Add yogurt and syrup and mix well.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Mix together the dry ingredients in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Make a well in the center of the dry ingredients and add the wet ingredients. Stir swiftly, until combined. The batter should be thick, but spoonable. Add milk if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spoon batter into muffin tins, filling about two-thirds full.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake 15-18 minutes or until toothpick inserted into center comes out clean.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool for 5 minutes before taking out of the tin.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-06-muffin.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed the recipe for these fairly closely, substituting Greek yogurt for the soy and whey isolate protein for the plant-based one in the original. I made 12 muffins, not 8 as the kits.eats' recipe indicated. The batter was very runny, and I was concerned the muffins wouldn't hold together. They did, although they didn't really rise much and they were a bit too chewy. (I don't think I over-mixed the batter — often the cause of a chewy muffin. I'll write more soon on how to troubleshoot things like flat muffin-tops.) The texture of the crumb was fine, but they were rather bland — they didn't taste much like banana &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; buckwheat (and the cacao was more of a crunch than a flavor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-06-muffin3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buckwheat flour, for what it's worth, does have slightly more protein than wheat flour, and I'll experiment with more protein-rich flours in my bakes in lieu of just adding a protein powder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-06-muffin2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some &amp;quot;Health&amp;quot; Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am looking for in a healthy muffin: lots of protein and fiber and very little sugar or sodium. Or, at least 5 grams of protein; at least 2.5 grams of fiber; less than 10 grams of sugar; less than 10 grams of fat; and less than 200 milligrams of sodium. (These numbers might seem arbitrary. In many ways, they are! The main questions I'm working with in this series are: can I make a muffin that has more protein than any ol' basic muffin, and can I make a healthy muffin that tastes great?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For comparison, &lt;a href=&quot;http://food.audreywatters.com/2021/10/04/what-is-a-muffin&quot;&gt;the Basic Muffin&lt;/a&gt; has 3.5 grams of protein; .7 grams of fiber; 5.4 grams of sugar; 3.8 grams of fat; and 238.5 milligrams of sodium. This Banana Buckwheat Protein muffin has 7.6 grams of protein; 2.7 grams of fiber; 8.5 grams of sugar; 2.5 grams of fat; and 189.3 milligrams of sodium. (Yes, it has twice the protein than the basic muffin, but that comes almost entirely from adding the two scoops of protein powder.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/06/what-is-a-healthy-muffin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/06/what-is-a-healthy-muffin</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Is a Muffin?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Great Muffin Experiment, No. 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when I bake cupcakes, Kin will call them &amp;quot;muffins&amp;quot; just to annoy me. &amp;quot;They're cupcakes,&amp;quot; I insist. &amp;quot;Are they?&amp;quot; he'll tease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are they, indeed. What exactly &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a muffin, and how is it different than a cupcake? &lt;em&gt;Or is it&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's easy to joke about confusing the two. Both are baked in muffin tins — muffin tins often lined with cupcake papers. And the etymology doesn't help clarify things — a cake baked in a cup seems obvious. But the word &amp;quot;muffin&amp;quot; is possibly derived from the Low German &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;muffen&lt;/em&gt;,&amp;quot; plural of &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;muffe&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;small cake.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/muffin&quot;&gt;Possibly, etymologists say&lt;/a&gt;, because what we know now as the small cake-like muffin is different from the small yeasted bread known as the crumpet or English muffin. It's confusing! (But Kin's jokes still aren't funny.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, ways we can and do distinguish the two: cupcakes can be frosted, for example; muffins are less likely to be, although they can be glazed. Muffins purport to be healthy; you can get away with eating one for breakfast, while it's generally frowned upon to eat a cupcake for the first meal of the day. I say &amp;quot;purport to be healthy,&amp;quot; because muffins are still quite sweet and even with &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; additions like flax seed and oats and dried fruit, they can contain about as much sugar and fat as a cupcake. There are, for what it's worth, about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fatsecret.com/calories-nutrition/starbucks/chocolate-chunk-muffin&quot;&gt;440 calories in the Starbucks Chocolate Chunk Muffin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the difference between a muffin and a cupcake is not in the ingredients or the calories or the topping or the time of day they're consumed. Rather, &lt;strong&gt;the difference is in how the batter is assembled&lt;/strong&gt;. Cupcakes are, as the name suggests, typically made the same way that cakes are: by creaming the butter and sugar, then adding the eggs and beating until light and fluffy. The dry ingredients — flour, salt, and baking powder, for example — are then added alternately with milk. Muffins are more akin to a quick bread insofar as the dry ingredients (including the sugar) are mixed together; the wet ingredients are mixed together separately; and then the two are combined quickly, without too much stirring, which would develop gluten and make the muffins chewy. Lumps are bad in your cake batter; lumps are fine in your muffin batter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This distinction works well right up until you consider all the &amp;quot;just add water&amp;quot; varieties of &amp;quot;instant&amp;quot; (read: microwavable) mixes. Then, I guess, it's quick breads all the way down.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of The Great Muffin Experiment, I will be making a variety of muffins in my quest for the perfect, &quot;healthy&quot; muffin. But let's start without any preconceived notion of what's &quot;healthy&quot; — I'll write about that next — and look and what goes into your basic muffin. 




&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Basic Muffin&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is based on the basic muffin recipe from Mark Bittman's &lt;em&gt;How to Cook Everything&lt;/em&gt; cookbook.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:18px&quot;&gt;Prep time: 10 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Cooking time: 20 minutes&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Servings: 12&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;·&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Calories: 133&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 Tbps melted butter&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;2 cups all-purpose flour&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/4 cup sugar&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1/2 tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;3 tsp baking powder&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 egg&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;1 cup milk, plus more if needed&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instructions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 400 F. Line 12 compartments of standard muffin tin with paper (or grease tin).&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Mix together the dry ingredients in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Beat the melted butter, egg, and milk in a bowl.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Make a well in the center of the dry ingredients and add the wet ingredients. Stir swiftly, until combined. The batter should be lumpy, not smooth but quite moist. Add more milk if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Spoon batter into muffin tins, filling about two-thirds full.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Bake 18 minutes or until toothpick inserted into center comes out clean.&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;Cool for 5 minutes before taking out of the tin.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-04-basic2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Some Baking Notes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we think of this as the &amp;quot;ur&amp;quot; muffin — a stretch, but bear with me — then there's lots of room for exploration and - apologies to Mark Bittman - improvement. All the ingredients are variables to be played with — more or different sugar, different flour, different fat, for starters. And that's some of what I'll explore throughout The Great Muffin Experiment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://audreywatters.s3.amazonaws.com/2021-10-04-basic.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But &amp;quot;ur&amp;quot; muffin or not, I found these to be quite bland, not surprisingly. I wouldn't complain too much about the level of sweetness, but the only real flavor came from the butter. The texture of the muffin was fine — perhaps a little dry. (I could have added more milk, I suppose, as Bittman recommends. I also could have cooked them a bit less than what the recipe called for, I think.) The biggest drawback, however, was that these didn't freeze well, which is something I am definitely looking for as I cannot eat a dozen muffins that quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(As such, I now have 10 rather dull and dry muffins that I have to do something with. How about &lt;s&gt;bread&lt;/s&gt; muffin pudding?!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/04/what-is-a-muffin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/04/what-is-a-muffin</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Muffin Experiment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I'm starting a new project, one I'm calling The Great Muffin Experiment. I'm going to document some of it here — and perhaps eventually it will become a standalone website (or subdomain). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project grows out of my 2021 turn towards a more healthy lifestyle: I've quit drinking, for starters. Fewer calories from booze has helped me to lose about forty pounds. But I also exercise a lot — yoga and recently powerlifting. The latter has made me particularly keen on monitoring how much protein I'm eating — all the better to make muscles. I make a smoothie with protein powder after our morning walk; I also eat a protein bar either before or after working out. All this — not just the increased protein intake — no surprise, has shifted the kinds of ads I get on Instagram (the only social media I'm really on these days). That is to say, I get a lot of ads for &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; snacks, particularly protein bars as, like a dummy, I've actually clicked through and purchased a couple different types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've also searched online for recipes that will fulfill my pre- and post-workout needs. In addition to the smoothie and the protein bar, I also eat some Greek yogurt (high in protein!) and a carb or some sort in the mornings. I love the &quot;Friends and Family Granola&quot; Recipe in Roxana Jullapat's &lt;em&gt;Mother Grains&lt;/em&gt; cookbook, for example, although it's 1) rather expensive to make and 2) rather high in calories; I've bought some protein cereal online — low in calories, but pretty damn flavorless. Most days, however, I like to blend a muffin in with the yogurt. The muffin gives the yogurt some texture; the yogurt gives the muffin some moisture and creaminess. Plus, I love to bake — and while dieting have rarely indulged in my creations, for some reason I've convinced myself that muffins are &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; — more on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in searching for &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; recipes — muffins or otherwise — one must wade through a real SEO swamp. I understand that food bloggers have to play the game that Google has set forth in order to appear in search results. Part of this project will be to mark up my data, my blog posts with the appropriate schema so that my stuff too can be found. I won't be making money through ads or sponsorships, and as such, I won't try to lure people to click on this site. (Indeed, I hope it's not discovered for a good long while as this is a nice quiet place to write without being found or followed.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than clicks, I'm interested in the science of making a healthy muffin, and more generally in the science of muffin-making. What even &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a muffin? How can you alter a basic muffin recipe and increase the protein or the fiber or decrease the sugar and fat (without turning to protein powder and sugar substitutes)? When do you use baking soda versus baking powder? How does banana or pumpkin puree or flax seed or coconut flour work as a substitute? That sort of thing...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I plan to write an essay that will accompany a recipe — each pair will examine one concept in muffin-making. Some of these recipes will be mine; some will be others'. I'll start with an explanation of &amp;quot;what is a muffin.&amp;quot; I'll write another one about &amp;quot;what is healthy&amp;quot; — for me, that is. What are my goals in making this baked good? The experiment will proceed from there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/02/the-great-healthy-muffin-experiment</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/02/the-great-healthy-muffin-experiment</guid>
        
        <category>muffins</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eating 'Healthy'</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been quite remiss in keeping this blog up-to-date, which is a shame considering &amp;quot;food&amp;quot; has been a major focus on my life lately. No doubt, I have put a lot of energy into what I cook and what I eat in order to distract me from my deep, deep grief at the loss of Isaiah. I also had a major health scare that led to the discovery of a (different) major health issue that prompted me to really re-evaluate what I'm doing with this aging body of mine. What I'm doing, more or less, is &amp;quot;getting healthy&amp;quot; — probably healthier than I've ever been in my life, which is weird to say at age 50. I've quit drinking — there's a lot to be written about that. I work out a lot — there's something to be written about that too, and although much of it is outside the purview of this blog, I do think a lot more now than I ever have before about what I eat, about my &amp;quot;macros.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last bit — particularly my efforts to get enough protein for my new powerlifting hobby (LOL, yes) — has had me looking for various recipes that will fulfill my insane hunger when I get home from the gym. While carbs seem to be very unpopular — keto whatever whatever — I'm not anti-carbs per se. I don't want to eat a lot of sugar though. And I don't want to eat too much fat. I don't want too much sodium. I would like a good amount of protein in my post-workout snack. So I've been baking muffins — &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; muffins — that I stir into a cup of Greek yogurt. And let me tell you, it's a hoot looking for &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; muffin recipes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, looking for any sort of recipe content online is frustrating. The whole SEO game has forced food bloggers into a certain style of writing — I get that. Whatever. But when it comes to hitting those keywords like &amp;quot;protein&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;healthy,&amp;quot; particularly with something that's really just a heavy cupcake, the recipes are ludicrous. So I'm going to start chronicling my experiments baking &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; muffins. A batch of muffins is about 12; we won't eat that many in a week or even two. But I think I can do an update once a month or so with a recipe and some thoughts about what &amp;quot;healthy&amp;quot; means in its context. It'll be fun! And it won't be SEO-optimized as I don't want anyone to find this site. Yet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/09/29/healthy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/09/29/healthy</guid>
        
        <category>healthy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dinner after Death</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the past three or so weeks, we have had dinner delivered to the house every night — or almost every night — thanks to the kindness of friends who want to support me following Isaiah's death. It's been a relief, no doubt, to not have to cook. It is hard, while grieving, to force myself to eat. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it's been a strange experience — quite different from the typical grieving process in which friends and family bring over meals. We're under stay-at-home orders, so the food is all ordered from restaurants that are doing delivery. The time that it arrives then has been dependent on a variety of factors — when it was ordered, how quickly the restaurant responds, how fast it gets in a car to our apartment. The latter was challenging too during the nights Oakland had a curfew because of the police riots. Dinner never showed up a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's made me realize how controlling I am over food. I like to line up the meals for the week. Then I know what I need from the grocery store. I manage how many nights in a row we'll have tacos, for example. (There is an excellent taqueria across the street, and folks have ordered us a lot of tacos. And that's fine! I love tacos. But probably not night after night, you know?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a lesson in grace and in letting go. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 08:20:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/15/death-dinner</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/15/death-dinner</guid>
        
        <category>grief</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Garlic and Onions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I'd have him chop the onions and garlic for me. He was so much more fastidious than me. I don't mind if they're all different sizes. I try to accomplish the prep work for meal quickly. He would spend so long, making sure everything was diced, not chopped, and uniformly so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will think of him every day, and I will have real reasons now to cry quietly as I chop the onions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 08:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/15/onions</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/06/15/onions</guid>
        
        <category>onions,</category>
        
        <category>grief</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
